welcome everyone
uh to the monthly q a it's a great
pleasure to be here again
uh reminder of what the format is
we will answer questions uh first from
patrons
and then questions also from people who
belong uh
to the sang in the discord server and
then open things up to
uh the general chat so i'd like to start
first of all
uh with a quick question from a patron
rachel hayden
i don't know if i've uh interacted with
you before rachel so thank you very much
for your support
um and here's rachel's question there is
a massive
book list contained within uh the
awakening from the meeting crisis series
yeah there is
uh which i've just finished the series
uh thank you for finishing that series
it's that's i know it's it's quite a
challenging uh thing to engage in so
thank you for doing that
is there a recommended starting point
for exploring these
i've already ordered by harry
frankfurt
and aspiration by agnes callard due to
personal interest in this topic
and i noticed that a few of the books
were either very highly praised such as
the sovereignty of the good
by iris murdoch or mentioned repeatedly
such as transformative experiences by
l.a paul
i do not have a background in western
philosophy so i'm wondering if there
might be a sort of general
order to go in old to new new to old
easy to heart certain lineages
thank you so rachel first of all let me
give you um
an order that i would recommend going
through the books that you've noted here
i would recommend starting with uh the
sovereignty of the good
and then moving to frankfurt's book
then moving to l.a paul's book
transformative experience
and then moving to agnes keller's book
aspiration um and the reason for that
is because there's an important sense
with
some of the books directly presuppose uh
one another so aspiration
uh presupposes that you've read the uh
transformative experience
i think transformative experience is
very much helped if you've read
sovereignty of the good
the sovereignty the good and
also talk to each other in terms of
contrast
um so a general principle though that i
thought that i followed in the advice i
gave you
is i went from old to new
and that's generally a good idea when
moving through these books
um the easy to hard isn't as good a
strategy
lineages are a little bit more more more
challenging
uh to work out but a general strategy is
to move through it uh chronologically
because of the way in which uh later
arguments
and theories build on previous arguments
and theories
especially uh when i'm using them within
awakening from the meeting crisis um
so i would recommend uh pretty strongly
that you go
in historical order of the books that
are found
in awakening for the meeting crisis um
you might want to limit it to certain
uh like genres or sub-genres
for example there you know you might
want to go
in a chronological order
uh within uh sort of
what you might call a theological uh a
thought
or chronological uh chronological order
within psychological thought
uh things like that so
generally going chronologically is the
best you may be able to subdivide it
into some subgenres
but that's usually the best strategy for
the way i'm making use of the material
with an awakening from the meeting
crisis
okay so the next one is from steam
a regular patron good to see you again
tian i would like
uh to hear you speak on some
psychopathology in general and or
confusion and psychosis in particular
that might not be your field of study
but i'm curious to hear uh
if not i have another question how is it
going with your chocolate addiction
so i my chocolate addiction
is going fairly well right now um
largely but not keeping very much
chocolate
in my proximity uh seems to be a pretty
effective strategy
um so i think i will talk a little bit
more time to
your first question so there's a lot of
work
coming out that i think is converging on
the idea
that you can see psychopathology as
lying on a continuum and it is a
continuum
basically in terms of salient regulation
or dysregulation which has ultimately do
with ways in which relevance realization
uh can become pathological
because it has lost cognitive
flexibility
so on so uh there's there's vatican
crispy
and then there's the work of us and the
work of kapoor
i won't go into a particular the basic
idea is this
um that psychosis
is when the relevance realization of
machinery
is hyperactive in the sense
that it is finding too many patterns
that
are not there and so it's
grabbing too much information as
relevant in an important way
and realizing patterns that are not real
patterns
part of how this is probably happening
is a decrease in the ability to
distinguish causal patterns
from correlational patterns this is
seems to be the case
within schizophrenia on the other end of
the spectrum
would be people who might be
not noticing enough patterns now this is
called the autistic end of the spectrum
and it's a little bit problematic
uh because autism is itself a spectrum
disorder
but the general idea here is there's a
family of
disorders known as autism
and one of the features that they share
in common
is that people are not no they're so
if the the psychotic person is seeing
too many patterns
that are not there the autistic person
is not seeing enough of the patterns
that are actually there
so they are discounting too many of the
real they're discounting too many real
patterns
they're not finding salient enough
enough of the real patterns
and so what a lot of people are now
talking about
is strategies instead of trying to deal
with
the ideation the ideas that people have
or
strategies that deal with the affect how
people
are effectively aroused or their affect
is too intense or too
flat people are talking about how can we
help modify
uh and help people more properly
regulate
their their their salience landscaping
uh so that we can bring people up
that's the right way right word uh
who are not noticing enough uh patterns
as relevant
and we can regulate down uh people who
are noticing
too many patterns as relevant so
but one of the interesting things about
this for me we never wrote it down which
is
unfortunate but what i was originally
working with
tim lillacroft and blake richards on the
original
uh relevance realization paper
in 2007 2008
i remember going on a walk with blake
and he actually proposed
that he thought that the relevance
realization theory that we were working
out
uh would would uh be the basis for a way
of
re-understanding uh psychopathology in a
much more coherent
and integrated fashion and i wish we had
made that an actual formal prediction
because it looks like it's coming to
confirmation
and so that would be my answer to the
question of what's the relationship
what do i see the relationship between
ideas around relevant realization
and ideas about psychopathology
so the next question is from karima
who's a patron and who support
both in terms of financial support and
the continual contributions
uh she makes to the sangha the discord
community
it's fantastic the squad server
community so uh
welcome karinama as always um so kareem
asks the question please elaborate on
the five factors of inquiry and
mindfulness my
inquiry mindfulness meditation in
regards to those things thoughts
this came up on the discord sit today
with some of us needing more definition
physical sensations and identified
emotions held in the body are more
easily entertained for examination than
our thoughts
yes so just quickly what are the five
factors of inquiring mindfulness
uh the first factor of inquiring
mindfulness is vigilance
this is the capacity that gets us to
move away from the familiar
um superficial aspects of our experience
and gets us to try and probe to what is
unfamiliar uh
more profound aspects of our experience
sensitivity this is the factor that
tries to set
us set our experience back in motion
uh an analogy i use is letting your
experience unfold as a movie rather than
being satisfied
with snapshots that you take of it with
uh with your mind
acuity acuity is to pull apart the
different
uh layers and components of an
experience
that's when you're for example when
you're experiencing pain
um you can pull apart sort of the felt
nastiness the tension
the emotional reaction the sense of
threat etc
and and then there is noticing
noticing is to pay attention to three
different
sort of uh orientation centers
how is your body responding to this how
are you embodying
this this the state how are you
emotionally responding to
what not but now what are the particular
emotions but what is your like what is
your heart your emotional center doing
is it racing is it freezing
what's it doing and then what's your
mind doing again not so much not what
you're thinking
but is your mind speeding up slowing
down is it fragmenting is it
dulling is it sharpening what's
happening
you apply the five factors of inquiring
mindfulness on distractions
the idea here is so this is not
something you do as a novice and not as
a novice
you learn to step back label your
distraction return your attention to the
breath
you do this for a long enough time until
you you get to a certain stage
and then what you can do once you've got
some stabilization is
when you step back and look at your
distraction to label it
you actually apply the five factors of
inquiring mindfulness
the idea about that is that your
distractions reflect
automatic and often persistent patterns
and how you're making sense of things
how your mind works your mind and body
and heart work
and by doing inquiring mindfulness on
your distractions
you could actually turn them from
obstacles to meditation as arenas
in which you train a more profound
capacity for
insight vipassana as karima rightly
points out
um applying the five the five factors of
inquiring mindfulness to thinking
is particularly hard um because
finding that space between being aware
of it and being
aware within it is very hard so it's
sort of it's relatively easy
it's not super easy but it's relatively
easy when i'm in pain
notice in pain that i part of me can
sort of step back and not be in the pain
and look at it it's much harder to try
to
step back and look at a thought without
being within the thinking process
typically what happens and what happens
for a long time for novices
is when you step back and try to look at
thinking
you either do one of two things you fall
back into the thoughts you're in the
thinking and you're
wrapped up in the content of your
thoughts and then you are
you've lost uh mindfulness or you stay
disconnected from the thinking process
and it just sort of disappears away into
nothing
okay so one of the things you can do
right is and i did mention this uh
when we talked about this so um i'm
hoping i'm not just being repetitive i
hope i can
bring it out in it in a way that's
that's adjusted to the novelty of the
situation for you guys
um so one of the things that works
one of the tricks of the trade is to try
and pay attention to the voice
so when i'm applying the five factors of
acquiring mindfulness
what's unfamiliar to me typically
so i'm applying vigilance is i try to
not to concentrate on
what my thinking is let's do
just with sort of inner sentences uh
because uh
um i i can't do a complete lesson here
right so i do the vigilance because i
step back
and what i normally do is i look at what
the content of my thought is
but in vigilance i try to get below i
try to get below that familiar surface
i try to get at the voice of my thoughts
and the identity bound up with that
voice
is is it my voice um what age
is the voice what like is it a whiny
voice
is it uh a thrashing voice so
i pretend as if i like as if i was on
a bus and there was somebody sitting
beside me and i wasn't looking at them
but i
they're speaking a language i don't know
and so i'm trying to pick up on their
voice
and then i'm trying to pick up on their
age of their voice perhaps
the gender of the voice uh the emotional
state of the voice
and trying to and i try to be right
what's
sensitivity to that well i i'm trying to
pick up on
how that is unfolding is it unfolding
rapidly
is it unfolding slowly um is
are there pauses or gaps in it
the uh so so we
that's i've done the vigilance i've done
the sensitivity uh the acuity
right you but notice i already got some
of the acuity going
i try to notice different components of
this like i said i try to notice
um the aspects of the voice that has to
do with
you know is the
voice my voice is it someone else's
voice
is it a voice from me now is it a voice
from someone else now
from someone else some other time um
are there is there one voice is there
multiple voice and so
it's it's it it is tricky to to do these
just in sequence because
i go but if i was to try and put it into
sequence i shift to looking at the voice
i let the voice unfold i pay attention
to tempo texture
i then pull apart these aspects of it
right and then i try to notice how
my body my heart and my mind are
responding
to that that voice how it's flowing
and the different parts that i've pulled
apart with acuity
and of course i didn't do the fifth
factor uh when i was talking about the
five factors earlier
the fifth factor is reminding which is i
try to stay within mindfulness
i try to stay in inquiry through moving
observation through soft vigilance
rather than inquiry through the posing
of questions the uh the offering of
inferential justification
explanation uh etc
so i hope that was helpful um that's a
very tricky one
um and it takes a quite a bit of
practice
what i can report is that when this gels
for people
they often find it a very transformative
experience they often find it
very transformative to realize that the
voice in their head
sometimes isn't theirs and i don't mean
anything psychotic about it
or even if it's theirs it's not it's not
them as an adult it's them as a 10 year
old or something like that
so try that and see if that's helpful
rob uh so rob is a great patron great
supporter i always enjoy spending
uh time with rob so rob writes i think
i've noticed people sometimes
self-center the words like have
or having after diving deep into people
like you or eric from
yes while i understand language and
perception are closely integrated
interrelated
is it extreme to frequently reframe the
language you generate into being mode
style
i guess do you try to think and talk
with being mode expressions or having
mode expressions
purposefully or does the choice of the
words and phrases we use
afford our inter and intrapsychic
landscape through their use and
expression
i think that's an excellent question and
i do try to
correct my language so that
my language is mode appropriate to the
mode that is appropriate
to the situation at hand so if i'm in a
situation in which
it is appropriate to be in the having
mode i do try
that's usually something i can just
allow happen but
if i'm in a situation in which the being
mode is more appropriate
one of the things i do to try and
trigger the restructuring into the being
mode
and maintaining myself within it is to
actually
use uh more being mode expressions and
language
but notice what i said that isn't a
across the board
trying to replace having mode with being
mode language
if that's what's happening i would argue
that that's actually a misunderstanding
of from and a misunderstanding of how
i've been using from
the point is not that the hamming mode
is bad or the being mode is good
um or that you should at all times in
all places in
all ways try to always be in the being
mode that's a mistake
the mistake right the thing you're
trying to correct
is modal confusion sometimes you should
be
in the in the having mode and therefore
having language is completely
appropriate sometimes you need
to be in the being mode and therefore
you can help to structure that by using
language
that is more directly appropriate to
the being mode so
i think it's important to
be sorry
i hope this doesn't sound hack made
or cliche it's important to be wise in
this
it's important not it's important right
to
be flexibly responsive with the
discerning
eye to the situation you're in
the mode that is appropriate and the
language that is appropriate to that
mode
for me this is part of well you know the
promise i make
uh when i'm doing the five promises you
know in reverence and respect
for the power and promise of speech i
promise
not to speak foolishly or falsely but to
speak wisely in the aspiration to
enlightenment
so noting how much speech and humanity
are woven together i always try to use
my language
wisely but wisely doesn't mean in
a formulaic fashion it means with
reflexible discernment
like i just said so i think it's very
important um
to uh to try to
meet that promise you know my it's a
version of
the traditional training precepts but
it's important to not meet it
formulaically but meet it with finesse
and wisdom
uh so now a question from alex
siminov who's part of the discord sanger
uh welcome alexi it's always great to
have you
here so this is a fair long question i
will try to
go through it i hope at a reasonable
pace so people can follow along
after i did a long contemplation of what
is important in my life a few years back
i realized that two things are
of crucial importance self-actualization
through work
and family i suspect that most people
put these two
on top as well sometimes in different
order yes
but i found it impossible to make
consistent progress on both at the same
time
so for a few years i had to sacrifice
family part and go 100
optimizing for self-actualization
through work
i believe this is the right way for a
man to approach this prioritization
problem when time
attention and resources are not enough
to attack both problems
that bears fruit but it is very it is a
very lopsided way of living that is
ultimately counterproductive what would
be a wise philosophical way to approach
this challenge
in your experience ps
i really like when you show applications
of ancient philosophy practices to solve
day-to-day
problems like above i can't quite see
all of the question
i do not like some of the latest
uh let me see if i can move this a
little tiny bit
i uh i do not like some of the latest
here it is uh discussions would seem to
towards more theoretical dimensions
of philosophy yeah um
so some of that yeah so uh i'll last
that the ps
thing first yeah so trying to
it's always trying to toggle between and
um
between those two concerns um allowing
um a discussion in which the philosophy
is articulating
um the terms bringing clarification uh
you know making sure that when things
are not confused or we're not
equivocating
um introducing new conceptual vocabulary
and theoretical grammar
and of course that's also responsive to
my
interlocutor uh because where
they are particularly put pitched on
where they are trying to modulate their
cognition and consciousness
in order to try and get a better optimal
grip
um on situations um
so i understand that what you're saying
it is a good
um also to always try and bring
that philosophical understanding
back into transforming how you're
actually
at work in the world
and i just want to say how important
this is alexis point
you need to be doing both um and you
need to be doing them both in a
coordinated manner and that's why the
greeks actually had two words for wisdom
they had sophia and francis
and aristotle particularly talks about
this and sophia is that project
of right trying to get the the
principles
worked out it's much more it's often
called theoretical wisdom
um i'm not quite happy with these terms
but perhaps they're helpful where
phronesis is
right is a contextually sensitive how
can i be wise and virtuous
in this context how can i bring the
principles
into practice how can i actualize those
within the process in which i am
participating
and so wisdom always requires sophia and
phoniesis
and the integration of them together
let's see if we can also now fold that
back into
alexis question so this is a perennial
problem
it shows up in many sages
in fact in different cultures at
different times
um so siddhartha katama famously and of
course many people criticize him for
this
abandoned his family after he had seen
the four
signs that sort of shook him out of um
his complaints he
woke him up to how um how out of touch
he was
with reality um
when he decided he needed to pursue
enlightenment he abandons his family
he abandons his wife and children and of
course
many of us would regard that as highly
immoral
i regard that also something that i've i
personally
find unthinkable in uh frankfurt's sense
it's not something i could bring myself
to do to that extreme but alexi points
out
that okay
we might not be doing that but the myth
has relevance the myth has relevance
marcus aurelius talks about the same
thing about relating to his
like his wife things like that it's like
we might we might not be doing the
extreme but myths als often
they make things more extreme it's like
putting things under a magnifying glass
so that we can more readily see we can
more really get the joints we can more
readily articulate
the pattern and the problem that we're
wrestling with so
the myth is relevant because we are
often facing
exactly the kind of question that alexi
asked
and this is a difficult question like
there's a it's not a question
that i can give you a rule for or an
answer to
it's like the question um of how do i
decide between justice and compassion
so sophia can work out
we can and we're doing it a lot in our
culture right now you know we can
discuss what
justice is and get discuss what
compassion is
and can discuss you know their relative
tradeoffs you can do all that that's
very very different
the phronesis of but what do i do here
now
jesus of nazareth gave this amazing and
it's wonderfully
famous parable of the prodigal son
and the prodigal son is exactly a
parable
in which there is no resolution it looks
like a narrative but it's not it it
actually
it actually explodes as a narrative it
self-destructs as a narrative
because the point of the prodigal son is
there is no final resolution
between justice and compassion and at
different times in your life
you will identify with the prodigal son
or the elder son or the father
and to try and resolve between those
things is actually an
inhuman thing to do somebody says
somebody who says justice should always
trump trump
compassion is becoming inhuman
somebody who says compassion should
always trump justice
is becoming inhuman somebody who says
here's the authority
that will always decide between justice
and compassion is becoming inhuman
the parable of the prodigal son is
profound
precisely because of how it introduces
us
to this and then when jesus of nazareth
says and the kingdom of heaven is like
this
do you see what he's doing he's saying
the kingdom of heaven
is a place in which we are confronted
with the profundity
of these irrevol irresolvable tensions
but we somehow have
the wisdom to live through them in the
best possible way
on a case-by-case basis so that
i'm i'm doing this as a very long way of
saying to alexi
i don't want to give any rule and there
and there is no rule to give about this
i think what i would recommend to you is
what i started this with which was the
answer to your p the ps
you need to do a lot of work practicing
sophia thinking about it and i know you
don't like this as much
but you need to do a lot of work getting
very clear about the principles
and then you need to do a lot of work in
the mindfulness practices
and the wisdom have i pray hypatia
practices i'm bringing
right i'm cultivating from nieces yes
but in this situation
what's my contextual sensitivity how am
i grocking this situation what's my
optimal grip on this situation
how do you know how do i be wise in this
situation because every virtue
is how to be wise in a way that's
appropriate to that situation
so i have to practice sophia and
phronesis sophia and from nieces sophia
and francis
and then you will know you will know
that right with finesse you'll know at
this point
in my life at this time well maybe no is
too strong
but you will at least make a wise
decision
about how to balance the relationship
between your commitment to family
and your commitment uh to
self-actualization
tillett the person who gave me this idea
about how to
understand these tensions talks about
the fact that we are perpetually in an
irresolvable tension
between individuation and participation
and again if we try to resolve
it or we try to come up with a rule for
resolving it or we try and say there's
an authority that's the father figure in
the prodigal son who can always decide
this we lose our humanity
the way we preserve our humanity and the
way we act best is to deeply cultivate
sophia
deeply cultivate phoniesis and then let
them self-organize
in the situation in the context
that's the best advice i can give you
so the next question is from another
patron vida
i'm not sure i've met you before either
veta so thank you for your support
regarding wonder versus curiosity in a
group last night the facilitator offered
a process
in response to your comments about
wonder to say i wonder
to ostensibly create a mind state of
wonder result in my group analysis and
critiqued
guised as wondering yes it's i
understand the point you're making
right wonder seems like an organic mind
state and can't really be contrived in
group processes
can it it can um
but i underst but i understand the point
you're making
uh the only times i've actually gotten
to what i think you prescribe here is in
cohen practice
uh see bring me the rhinoceros or madame
dialogues but those require a foundation
of understanding shunyata my question is
is having a temporary mindset of wonder
enough of a boost to move one who is
stuck in looping conceptualizations to
develop more
meta awareness or prajna uh ps saw
evidence that folk also think wonder
means regression to childhood
yeah that last one that wonder means
regression to childhood that's an in
that that's due to decadent romanticism
um yeah and uh um
that's you know the the idea that
wonder is something like what we have in
childhood woodsworth is
sort of a classic example of that and i
think
that needs to be seriously challenged uh
like socrates said that wisdom begins in
wonder
and you you mentioned cohen practice and
madame dialogues
things like that i think um and they um
and that they require the understanding
of shunyata
um i think that um socratic dialogue
uh also uh has the same thing uh because
of especially for its capacity to bring
people into
a state of emporia um so i think simply
asking i wonder
i agree with you people uh if they
haven't practiced
even if they have a conceptual
distinction i think of just sophia not
for lisa
even if they have a conceptual
distinction between wonder curiosity
if they haven't practiced right if they
have to practice in phronesis the
distinction
they're just going to fall into the
conflation at a procedural level of it
as you indicated they're just going to
fall into
critique and right and things like that
um
so i think what's needed uh and this is
start of the work
a lot of the work that i'm doing with
christopher master pietro and also with
guys henstock and jordan hall peter
lindberg and other people are doing it
there's all these things emerging
around the process that i call dialectic
and what
i mean by that is that a practice
of questioning but also
drawing people out amplifying them
getting them to reflect
it's a uh it's an ecology of practices
that then fits into a higher order
ecology of practices
and what it's designed to do is exactly
provoke
wonder it's designed to get people to
uh call into question
through a perspectival and participatory
transformation
how they're seeing things and how they
are showing up how they're seeing
and how they are being in a coordinated
fashion that's why almost all the
socratic dialogues
centered on topics around virtue because
when people
start to reflect on virtue they they
typically will bring in
uh they'll tend to bring in more
perspectival and participatory
uh knowing and so i do think they're
um this is something i take very
seriously i think there are ways
of getting people oriented that way
that's one part of it and then there are
ways of getting people into the flow
state within distributed cognition
and the flow state
is a cascade of insights and if you get
people in a flow state
with indestructible cognition and
they're doing socratic dialogue
they will you'll tend to get a
self-organization an emergence of wonder
that starts to happen where people first
start wondering but what they're saying
they wonder about other people but then
they start wondering about
right the very process of
intelligibility the very the with
the way things are unfolding for them
i think when you get that kind of deep
socratic wonder
that can be a powerful way of shifting
people in the way you're asking about
um but i think that requires a
pedagogical program
of practices to get people to do that
on a powerful basis i think simply
using the sentence string i wonder
um would be inadequate i think even
having just a deliberate intent i'm
going to wonder instead of being curious
is insufficient
you have to engage of course you should
be doing that you should be doing the
sofia
you should be doing the theoretical
reflection but you need the phronesis
practice if you're going to
actually engage in wonder as something
distinct from curiosity
and engage in it at a level that's deep
enough to engage perspectival and
participatory knowing
right in something like a flow state so
that deeper transformation
is actually possible
okay so now we're going to get some
further questions uh this
is from zazian das chenov a patron
what are your views on emotions mental
states and mental disorders as dynamic
computational processes guiding
rr and the self-organizing system of
mind and body uh first
that's the first part of the question
second do you think there are analogous
processes on the level
of society or civilization as a whole so
first words
emotions um i've already spoken about
mental disorders
uh when i answered stean's question
mental states that's an ambiguous term
if it means
consciousness um i'll have to put that
aside
so not quite put it aside that wasn't
the right way what i was thinking what i
meant what i was
putting it aside in my mind because i
was putting it into
a sort of category of uh a theoretical
category
i think about mental states if we
understand them
as states of consciousness that is
basically perspectival knowing
and so it's talked a lot about
perspectival knowing and how it works in
terms of salience landscaping
that's how it overlaps with the stuff
i've said about
mental pathologies and then the
salient landscaping will also map onto
what i want to talk about with emotions
so following on some sort of seminal
work uh by
uh by ronnie d'souza and then
and also especially by keith odly
and then following up on um
work by reed montague and others
i want to say that emotions are a
particular way in which we're doing
salience landscaping
to be angry is to uh
be like to be here now
to be you know in this state of mind
here now
uh salience landscaping in a particular
manner
and that makes sense because the process
of relevance realization is not called
calculation
uh re this is what i mentioned read
montague the difference between you and
a computer
is you care about the information you're
processing
why do you care well first of all you
can't process it all
neither can a computer but it doesn't
doesn't matter to the computer
you can't process it all and you care
about information because you're trying
to find the information that will help
you
care for yourself because you're an
autopoetic thing
you're constantly taking care of
yourself because you're constantly
engaged in the project
of making yourself making yourself at
many levels making yourself as an
identity yourself making yourself
as a mind making yourself as a living
thing
so emotions are ways in which that
affect that character look when i'm
doing relevance realization
i'm spending my very precious and very
limited time and resources
cognitive and conscious processing and
i'm spending it on trying to find
what will matter to me most sometimes
literally matter to me
like what's important to me take into me
what will
literally help me keep making
myself biologically
cognitively consciously and ultimately
existentially
and so emotions are the way in which
relevance realization the caring that is
an integral part of relevance
realization comes
into working memory as a particular kind
of salience landscaping that then
helps me find those affordances given to
me by participatory knowing
that i can make it it makes obvious the
affordances
that should be happening here notice how
emotions come
with come with this tremendous
amplification of what is
obvious and what is obvious to do
and what is available to you right now
and what the opportunity for
action is so that's what i think um
that's what i think um
all uh i could say right now not that's
not all that can be said
i hope it didn't sound like it was
saying that that's all i can say right
now
about the interconnections in terms of
relevance realization theory
and related ideas about perspectival and
participatory knowing
you can see how we can talk about in an
integrated fashion
emotions mental states
at least states of consciousness and
uh mental disorders is there something
analogous
to emotions at the level of distributed
cognition
i think very very much i think there
that groups
um are also caught up in the project
of trying to use their limited times and
resources
and that they are trying to
often care about the information that is
needed for the group to take care of
itself for the group to
uh maintain its existence
and of course that can fall into a
vicious form
uh one of the besetting sins of
bureaucratic forms
of distributed cognition is that project
of maintaining
themselves uh becomes so paramount
that they get sort of reciprocally
locked into it reciprocal narrowing
and they everything else falls right
into a bands
and all that matters is the information
that will help to maintain the existence
of the institution and you can get you
can get something that looks very
much uh like stubbornness
and you can get very much like sort of
something like rage
when the integra the integrity of that
project
is is threatened so i think there's
something very
uh analogous we're now moving to live
questions from the
chat i want to thank uh patreon
subscribers and everyone's watching
uh who's watching right now as always
your support is very crucial to
continuing to produce
the videos i'm producing um to support
the science we're doing
uh as i've mentioned uh you know the
contributions have
already funded two very i think what are
two two
excellent experiments so thank you for
that and everything we're doing in
general
uh to try and find solutions to the
meeting crisis
so the first question is from somebody
i'm very familiar with and always
pleasure to interact with
david swedlow who's also a patron uh we
seem to be actively cohering continually
of contact and a lightning strike of a
more energetic expression
of the we do you sense your present
awareness of the collective
here now-ness to clarify my meaning of
lightning strike i believe this strike
is the essence of the meaning crisis not
so much a problem to be solved
but an expression to be realized we seem
to be actively cohering
continuity of contact and a lightning
strike of a more
energetic expression of the we yeah
i i take it you're david you're saying
this sort of you sense this happening
um sort of culturally in general right
now i very much have that sense too
um
yeah yeah they hear now-ness
you know that they're i think i'm
sensing this sort of
a zeitgeist to use some hegelian terms
of exactly what david is saying and when
i'm starting to go
when i've gone to some conferences i've
just wow i can't believe that all of
this
all of these different communities of
practices and equalities and practices
are springing up
in which in various ways uh what what
david talks about
are happening and i think that's very
much um
um i think it's very much the response
to the meeting crisis
very much like a an awakening to it
that is enmeshed with it and i think the
way david is talking about
um and for me
um i i tend to be by
constitution and because of my own sort
of
uh pathologies ah
and character flaws um i tend to be
a pessimistic person a pessimistic
person by nature
and
and of course there's events happening
especially i'm a canadian especially
south of the border
that can throw gasoline on the fire of
despair
but
seeing all of this what david is putting
his finger on
and how powerful it is and how
it's so enlivening to people when it
happens to them and they
they and this is why i've been taking up
a lot of this talk about sacredness
because the language
that people use about this is the
language of sacredness
and and you know and i had a really
amazing conversation with
uh tim adeline on voice craft with uh he
was moderating with uh forest landry
about the whole problem uh so people are
making it central
both at the level of sophia and the
level of phronesis how do we
take th that ephemeral coherence
and how do we make it more long-standing
not in the sense that everybody's
always blissed out but how do these
ephemeral coherences
uh plug into a cultural disposition
of of awakening in that way
so the fact that that's now becoming a
central question and mine's as brilliant
as forest
uh are are putting are turning towards
it i think all of that is so deeply
deeply encouraging um i don't believe in
teleology i don't think that anything's
in
the world making that happen
other than us and the intelligibility
that's available to us in the world
and so i do think it is still a race i
do think it is not a foregone conclusion
um but i find it deeply encouraging and
so
um i share your recognition
uh david and it's having a profound
effect on me and it's helping it's
sensitizing me to seeing it more and
more
i hope it's not confirmation bias
there's enough people doing this
independently like yourself
that leads me to believe it's not
confirmation by us
here's a question from kira kroger who's
a
a regular from who is regular from the
meditation live stream good to see you
again
akira are you familiar with tyson yunka
porta who wrote santa
the jordan hall is recommended so all i
can say is
on the basis of jordan's recommendation
i have bought
the book i have bought the book it is
sitting on my bookshelf i can look at it
right now
but unfortunately i have not had the
chance to take it up
um i i i'm looking forward to doing this
so right now i'm currently ignorant
i've purchased a book and when i get a
gap
i intend to read it and so perhaps at a
later date i'll be able to give you
some more reflections on it you
so maybe you can come back to me in a
little bit more time i don't want to
speak out of ignorance
um i've seen him talk i think he
he was at the stove stole by peter
lindbergh
but it's not enough to go into depth or
to answer
to uh answer your follow-up questions
so there's now a gems jmes
to what extent do we need narrative for
identity our relation to the world and
each other
if the deal logos is the way forward man
is this a question
i'm wrestling with right now it was it
was that was a question that was at the
center
of the excellent we all agreed it was
excellent tia logos
between paul vander clay jonathan pajot
and myself and then i did a follow-up uh
with jordan hall that was also
excellent on dlo goes deeper than
narrative the point i was making there
is um that
deal logos is deeper than narrative uh
narrative comes later in development it
has to be extensively trained
deliberately practiced whereas dialogos
comes
naturally to human beings and it comes
earlier
children are into the logos even before
they're
right they're sort of full-fledged
cognitive agents i mean you can look at
the work of tomasello and all the stuff
that's going on now
even around language acquisition uh and
think about what would happen if you
took dialogue dialogue at least even
dialogue
out of narrative if narrative would like
collapse and i mean
also internal dialogue narrative would
collapse to something
much more like uh chronology it wouldn't
be the same but it would
it would lose a lot of what makes it
distinct from near chronology
so i think the logos is deeper than
narrative
and then i'm i'm teaching a course right
now on uh
on the uh on the elusive self the nature
and function of the self
and uh this question about how much
we definitely need narrative to train
uh identity to make it temporally
extended so that i can identify
with the non-logical version so i can
engage in non-logical identity
with myself as a five-year-old or with
myself as an 80 year old
and that's important for moral
responsibility and long-term planning
and adaptivity so narrative seems to be
central to that
but we shouldn't confuse the language of
training with the language of explaining
the fact that narrative helps me to
train
identity doesn't mean that
it is necessarily constitutive of
identity galen strassen in a very famous
article
and he's done some important work on the
nature of the self
argues that he doesn't experience
himself in a narrative fashion
and he's of course a profound
philosopher he's a moral agent
of course he does experience himself
dialogically
because he writes these articles
somewhat monologically but he's at least
go enters into dialogue uh with other
people
uh there's lots of people in for
e-cognitive science
who are talking uh about identity
being much more an embodied embedded
enacted thing
um that is that is occurring
before we have full-blown propositional
representation in language
um so i think that
narrat and then and then you get the
other end so i've talked about
how it proceeds and grounds and deeper
and then you get
the the post narrative the mystics
consistently telling us
we transcend beyond narrative we get to
something
uh beyond narrative or you get as i
mentioned earlier
you get you know a figure like jesus of
nazareth who
and also tremendous also examples from
the sufi tradition
of people using narrative to
self-destruct narrative
to fling people beyond narrative
into a post-narrative
uh mental state because narrative works
in terms of us
of stable roles a problem resolution
etc um and the whole point again of the
prodigal son is
there is no such resolution
you're put back into a dialogical mode
that is post-narrative
because the dialogue is a dialectic
between the
the the the the the the tension points
with the tone us i'm constantly i'm
constantly dialogically moving in a
post-narrative fashion
between justice and compassion between
individuation
and participation so i think we should
think of just
i think we should think sorry of
narrative as
something that is indispensable at
a stage in development kind of like
you know i'm thinking of piercing stage
but that if we lock
into that as the final word on
development
we are actually cutting ourselves off
from the deepest machinery by which
identity is formed and how that deeper
machinery can propel us beyond
a narrative identity an egocentric
identity
right to what has been some called sign
sometimes called the non-self
the true self right the self beyond
yourself
um etc and where people
claim to find a fullness of being
the next question is from tracy oh i get
to learn your name
this is the original naked blonde writer
first of all tracy
now that you're here more directly
i want to really thank you
your your honesty and your courage for
disclosing the struggles you've gone
through and
the way you have been so kind in in
in the your the words of encouragement
you give me by saying
how the work i'm doing has been helpful
to you
i want i want to thank you because that
has been deeply
helpful to me it
it means a lot when i can see
people responding deeply
to what i'm teaching in a way in which
they confront some of the most
profoundest challenges facing them and
they confront it
with a transformation
that carries them or at least is
carrying them through
those challenges so i want to thank you
very very much
for how you do all of that it means a
lot to me so thank you very much
your question is you said before that
it's not good to meditate when powerful
emotions aren't played
how to stay on track while coping and
here's tracy's relating
cp uh cpt cds that's chronic post
traumatic stress disorder
flashbacks and fears so what
totally i think for you for in your
situation
yes i think especially because of the
depth
of what you've done i think uh engaging
on
uh on using the five factors of
inquiring mindfulness
on those emotions that are coming up in
flashback and fear is powerful
i think directing meta towards them is a
powerful thing to do
the thing i'm going to talk about on
saturday especially uh
uh complex not chronic i think it might
be complex i'm sorry
it's both complex and and some of the
crack um
i missed it sorry i made a mistake there
i apologize
uh being precise about these things is
important amara just corrected me so
thank you for that correction
um um so
um
some of the practices i'm going to be
talking about on uh
on on saturday with stoicism especially
the view from above
can be very powerful also the active
open-mindedness
practices that help you learn how to
challenge
the biases that are at work with an
emotion as i said earlier
emotions are powerful salience
landscaping and they're adaptive
but because they're powerful they
adaptive they are also powerfully
biasing
and they can be powerful sources of
self-deception
and so also learning how to recognize
i i'm making some mistakes and slipping
up a little bit but i hope it was still
um resonant enough that people were able
to
um get into it and and pick up on the
flow of it
i want i want to thank you all for for
joining me in this q a i always find
these
q a so nourishing that's why i wanted to
be here
uh i really wanted to be here it would
have been easy to just say no i'm not
feeling well but
um the questions are getting longer but
not
in a verbose fashion they're getting
more complex
they're getting more profound they draw
me out more they lead me to
thinking that you know making
connections that i haven't made before
even
seeing potential pitfalls in my thinking
so just thank you so much
we do this every third friday of the
month i want to thank all the supporters
over patreon
uh if possible please consider
supporting me via patreon
i do not get any income from patreon
i do not take any income from it that
money goes into the vervenke foundation
it supports further video work
series work it supports direct
experimentation in labs
about addressing getting information
science for addressing the meaning
crisis please consider it
it would be very helpful uh you can
support my work on the meeting crisis at
patreon.com
please note we have a discord server
where people are having some really
influence
interesting conversations where this can
be continued um
you can check uh the description uh for
the link to this
um every saturday morning we are
doing a we we meet and we sit and then
we have saturday sanga
a dharma day in which i teach we have
i well i have taught everything that i
can currently teach
from the eastern traditions of buddhism
and taoism i'm now
trying to teach everything i can from
the western tradition following
mcclellan's uh the wisdom of hypatia
going through epicureanism not just the
sofria
but also the phronesis we've started now
moving into stoicism we've done some of
the sophia last saturday we'll do a bit
more and then we'll go into the promises
some of the practices and then we will
move into
the epicureanism is primary school
stoicism as high school
we'll move into the university of
neoplatonism
so thank you so much to amar who was
there
he's making everything work he's behind
the scenes curating he's correcting my
mistakes
um he's he's one of my dearest friends
he's my ever ever reliable
my friend in right a friend in need is a
friend indeed
uh techno mage um there uh
he he he rescues me frequently
um and with a generous and good spirit
so i thank him
very much for that so i hope to see you
all next month please invite other
people to join please invite other
people to
take a look at the meditation series to
take a look at
the voices with raviki take a look at
awakening for the meeting crisis there's
new series coming down the road
we have the new series out there with my
good friend and colleague
greg enriquez untangling the world not
just filmed the seventh one today and
released the third one today
and we are really wrestling with the
nature and function of consciousness
down the road we're going to have a
series on the elusive self and then
hopefully when covet lessons up
lightens up sorry bad verb there and we
also
and the funding is there uh the very big
uh series which i put in so much work
into
um after socrates so
looking forward to seeing you all take
care everyone
bye-bye